Register of the William A. Drayton Papers, 1913-1946.
Hoover Institution Archives
William A. Drayton Papers
1913-1946
74090
Hoover Institution Archives
2 manuscript boxes, 1 envelope (0.9 linear feet)
Correspondence, reports, memoranda, speeches and writings, and photographs, relating to Serbia during and after World War I.
Drayton, William A.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1974.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Scope and Contents note
Correspondence, reports, memoranda, speeches and writings, and photographs, relating to Serbia during and after World War I.
Biographical/Historical note
American volunteer, Serbian army; member, Serbian delegation, Paris Peace Conference; Inter-Allied commissioner, Bulgarian Atrocities Commission.
Commission interalliee sur les violations des conventions de la Haye et du droit international en general commises de 1915 `a 1918 par les Bulgares en Serbie occupee.; Paris Peace Conference (1919-1920); Serbia--History.; World War, 1914-1918--Peace.; World War, 1914-1918--Yugoslavia.; World War, 1914-1918.; Yugoslavia.
- Diary, November 11, 1918-December 17, 1918
  Scope and Contents note
  Diary and diary notes, arranged chronologically.
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1917-1946
  Arranged alphabetically by last name of correspondent.
  - Army and Navy Club of America (Box 1)
  - Brandigen, E. D.
  - Commission for the Peace Conference in Ljubljana
  - Committee for a Fair Trial for Draja Mihailovich
  - Curwen, Mary
  - Drayton, Kolman
  - Gavrilovitch, Milan
  - Independent
  - Jovanovich, M.
  - Karovitch, Pavle
  - MacKinnon, M. L.
  - Milosavljevitch, Lazar
  - New York Herald
  - Pashitch, Nikola
  - Phillips, William
  - Sachutch, Kaross
  - Serbian Red Cross
  - Serbian Relief Fund
  - Serbian Society of Great Britain
  - U.S. A.E.F. Headquarters
  - U.S. Embassy London, Office of the Military Attache
  - U.S. Passport Bureau
  - Vesnitch, Milenko
  - Witton, M.
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS
  Drafts of speeches and writings, arranged alphabetically by title.
  - "Dalmatia." (Box 1)
  - "Financial Scheme for Serbia."
- SUBJECT FILE, 1913-1920
  Correspondence, clippings, memoranda, and printed material, arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - American Commission to Negotiate Peace, Paris, 1919 (Box 1)
  - Banat, Serbian territorial claims, 1919
  - Biographical file
    - "American Who Will Fight for Serbia." by Hayden Church, 1918
    - Certificate of exemption from military service
    - Delegation of the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes. Letters to the mother of W. A. Drayton
    - Letters of introduction and recommendation
    - "A Young American Friend of Serbia."
  - Bulgarian Military Occupation of Serbia, 1915-1918
  - Bulgarian-Serbian frontier claims and reparations, 1919-1920
  - Cer Mountain, battle, August, 1914
  - Georgevitch, T. R., "The Truth about Rumanes in Serbia", Paris, 1919 (Box 2)
  - Goricia, Italian occupation, 1918
  - Interallied Commission, Paris, 1919
    - Report on the Violations of the Hague Convention, by the Bulgarians in Occupied Serbia, 1915-1918
  - International credit and international government currency
  - Italian occupied territories, 1918-1919, treatment of inhabitants
  - Italian-Yugoslav territorial disputes, 1919
  - Jugoslav Committee in London. "Austria-Hungary's Effort to Exterminate Her Jugoslav Subjects."
  - Lazic, Ant., "Ethnographic Frontier of Italy, Yugoslavia, Germany." (In French)
  - Montenegrin National Assembly, Deputies, 1906-1913
  - Paris Peace Conference, 1919
    - Commission on Reparations of Debts -- Project for Treaty with Bularia
    - Delegation of the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes
      - Albania
      - Dalmatian question
      - Frontiers between the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes and the Kingdom of Italy
      - Goritza and Gradiska
      - Istria
      - Memorandum concerning the claims of Serbs, Croats and Slovenes
      - Military effort of the Serbs, Croats and Slovenes in the war of 1914-1918
      - North Frontier
      - Persecutions of Slovenes and Croats under Italian occupation
      - Serbo-Bulgarian relations
      - Triest
      - Economic and Financial Section. Memorandum concerning the Peace Treaty with Austria
    - Democratic Autonomist Party of Fiume
  - "Report of a Yugoslav Interned in Italy," Paris, 1919
  - Serbia, World War I, Reconstruction and relief
  - Serbian Army offensives, Autumn, 1918
  - Smodlaka, J., "Jugoslav Territorial Claims", Paris, 1918
- MISCELLANY
  Calling cards and other miscellaneous materials, arranged as listed.
  - Calling cards (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous
- PHOTOGRAPHS (Envelope A)
  Includes 33 photographs in 1 envelope: 28 photos of atrocities committed by the Bulgarian Army in occupied Serbia, 1915-1918. 3 photos of William A. Drayton as an officer in the Serbian Army during World War I. 1 photo of Mary and Margaret Brebrier.